Norman Podhoretz Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Norman Podhoretz Papers 1950-1986
MSS60103
Podhoretz, Norman
11,500 items
43 containers
15.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author and editor. Correspondence, memoranda, diary, journal, writings, speeches, transcripts of interviews, newspaper clippings, printed materials, and other papers relating primarily to Podhoretz's career as an author and editor of Commentary.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bellow, Saul.; Camus, Albert, 1913-1960.; Cleaver, Eldridge, 1935-1998--Correspondence.; Decter, Midge--Correspondence.; Disraeli, Benjamin, 1804-1881.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997--Correspondence.; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984--Correspondence.; Leavis, F. R. (Frank Raymond), 1895-1978.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003--Correspondence.; Podhoretz, Norman.; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004--Correspondence.; Southern, Terry--Correspondence.; Trilling, Diana--Correspondence.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975--Correspondence.; Vonnegut, Kurt--Correspondence.; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972.
Subjects
American literature.; American periodicals.; Censorship.; Conservatism.; Criticism.; Liberalism.; Military readiness.; Poverty.; Racism.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Places
Asia--Description and travel.; Australia--Description and travel.; India--Description and travel.; Middle East--History.; New York (N.Y.)--Intellectual life--20th century.; United States--Intellectual life--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Social conditions--20th century.
Titles
Commentary (New York, N.Y.)
Occupations
Authors.; Editors.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Norman Podhoretz, author and editor, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Podhoretz in 1981. Additional material was deposited in 1983-1986.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1930, Jan. 16 Born, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1950 A.B., Columbia University, New York, N.Y. B.H.L., Jewish Theological Seminary, New York, N.Y.
1950 1951 Fulbright Fellow, Cambridge University, England
1952 B.A. (Kellett Fellow), Cambridge University England
1953 1955 Served in U.S. Army
1956 Married Midge Rosenthal Decter
1956 1958 Associate editor, Commentary
1957 M.A., Cambridge University, England
1959 1960 Editor-in-chief, Looking Glass Library
1960 Editor-in-chief, Commentary
1964 Published Doings and Undoings: The 50s and After in American Writing. New York: Farrar, Straus
1966 Edited The Commentary Reader: Two Decades of Articles and Stories. New York: Atheneum
1968 Published Making It. New York: Random House
1979 Published Breaking Ranks: A Political Memoir. New York: Harper & Row
1980 Published The Present Danger: Do We Have the Will to Reverse the Decline of American Power. New York: Simon and Schuster
1982 Published Why We Were in Vietnam. New York: Simon and Schuster
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Norman Podhoretz cover the period 1950-1986 and consist of correspondence, subject material, speeches and writings, printed matter, and miscellaneous material. The collection is organized into five series: General Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, and Addition.
Norman Podhoretz was educated as a literary critic under such teachers as Lionel Trilling at Columbia University and F. R. Leavis at Cambridge University. Early in his career, Podhoretz was an advocate of left-wing ideology. He was later to break from the predominantly leftist and liberal New York intellectual community and become a leading spokesman for a conservative philosophy, using Commentary as a vehicle for discussing neoconservative ideas. His papers document the development of his career as a writer, editor, and social and political thinker.
Podhoretz throughout his career corresponded with many prominent writers, critics, editors, politicians and other public figures. The bulk of the General Correspondence series is formed from letters in Podhoretz's correspondence files at Commentary that were deemed inappropriate for the magazine's archive maintained by the American Jewish Committee. Letters within the General Correspondence document Podhoretz's involvement in literary and political activities. Among the correspondents are Eldridge Cleaver, Allen Ginsburg, Lillian Hellman, Daniel P.Moynihan, Susan Sontag, Terry Southern, Diana Trilling, and Kurt Vonnegut. There are also letters concerning Podhoretz that were sent as enclosures to him, for example, a letter from Lionel Trilling to Eliot Cohen, then editor-in-chief of Commentary. Although most of the correspondents are represented by only one or two letters, the issues and ambiance of the time are chronicled in these communications.
Topics discussed in the General Correspondence series include censorship of Podhoretz's writing as well as other literary works, endorsement of political candidates, support for political points of view, and discussion of social and cultural issues such as racism and poverty. Podhoretz's philosophical shift can in part be traced through the General Correspondence. Letters related to individual works by him are filed in the Speeches and Writings File series.
Featured in the Subject File is Podhoretz's trip to India, Australia, and Asia in 1973, including a journal containing sketches of people and places encountered in the various countries he visited. His trip to Australia in 1982 to promote The Present Danger is also well documented. Another file in the series concerns Daniel Patrick Moynihan's campaign for the Senate from New York in 1976.
The most extensive series is the Speeches and Writings File including interviews, speeches, undergraduate writings, short stories, articles, and books. Among the undergraduate writings are Podhoretz's notebooks from a course in nineteenth-century British poetry taught by Lionel Trilling. These notebooks are annotated by Trilling. Material from Podhoretz's years at Cambridge includes copies of the English Tripos along with notes, drafts of his thesis on Benjamin Disraeli, and notes from a class on the English moralists. The collection also includes three unpublished short stories written when Podhoretz was in the army.
The Articles subseries in the Speeches and Writings File contains a representative sampling of Podhoretz's literary, social, and political criticism, including a number of unpublished pieces. Drafts, galleys, published copies of articles along with correspondence and research material are often present. Within the Articles file is an expanded version of Podhoretz's thesis on Disraeli that he attempted to have published in Scrutiny in 1953. Included with the essay is F.R. Leavis's critique of the piece. Among the other literary essays in the collection are "Edmund Wilson: The Last of the Patricians," "The Know Nothing Bohemians," "The Adventures of Saul Bellow," "Prurience Subverted, or the Redemption of Candy," "In Defense of Editing," "Camus and His Critics," and "F.R. Leavis: A Reevaluation."
Some of Podhoretz's social and political writings include "Masses, Classes, and Social Criticism," "The New American Majority," and "J'Accuse," along with other articles expounding Podhoretz's neoconservative point of view on subjects such as defense, the Middle East, and Vietnam, most of which appeared in national magazines and newspapers.
Material exists in varying degrees to document the creation, production, and reception of Podhoretz's five published books. In addition to drafts, galleys, and page proofs, the collection includes correspondence from publishers and readers, book reviews, and research material. The correspondence and book reviews impart a sense of how Podhoretz's books were received and how he reacted to the mixed reception he met his works.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
General Correspondence, 1951-1982
Subject File, 1960-1982
Speeches and Writings File, 1950-1982
Miscellany, 1958-1982
Addition, circa 1953-1986
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1951-1982 (Box 1)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, with attachments.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1951-1982, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1)
- Subject File, 1960-1982 (Box 2-3)
  Correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clippings, notes, printed material, and journal.
  Arranged alphabetically subject.
  - Abzug, Bella, 1976 (Box 2)
  - American Jewish Committee, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Commentary, 1962-1980, undated (Box 2)
  - Idi Amin, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Jerusalem Conference on Terrorism, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Moynihan, Daniel P., 1975-1976, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Reagan retreat on Defense, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Trip to Australia (Box 3)
    - India, and the Orient, 1973, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Promotion of The Present Danger, 1982 (Box 3)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1950-1982 (Box 3-31)
  Typewritten drafts with handwritten annotations, galleys, page proofs, notes, research material and correspondence relating to speeches, interviews, books and other writings by Podhoretz.
  Arranged by presentation, including interviews and speeches, undergraduate writings, short Stories, articles, and books, and therein chronologically. Primary material is filed first, followed by supplementary material (e.g. correspondence, research material). When only printed versions of articles exist, these are filed at the end of the article subseries in chronological order.
  - Interviews and speeches (Box 3)
    - 1962-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980-1982, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate writings (Box 5)
    - 1950-1952, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Short stories (Box 5)
    - "The European Experience of Private Roy Summers," undated (Box 5)
    - "The Perfect Subject," undated (Box 5)
    - "The Separation of the Shells," undated (Box 5)
  - Articles (Box 5)
    - "Disraeli as a Political Novelist," circa 1953 (Box 5)
    - "A Season of First Novels," New York Times Book Review, 1957? (Box 5)
    - "Solitary or Solidary?," New Yorker, 1957? (Box 5)
    - "The Article as Art," Harpers, 1958, and collected in Doings and Undoings, 1964 (Box 5)
    - "Edmund Wilson: Last of the Patricians," The Reporter, 1958 and collected in Doings and Undoings, 1964, (1 folder) (Box 5, Box 6)
    - "The Future of International Beat," Esquire, 1958 (Box 6)
    - "The Know-Nothing Bohemians," Partisan Review, 1958, and collected in Doings and Undoings, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "Norman Mailer: The Embattled Vision," Partisan Review, 1959 and collected in Doings and Undoings, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "Edmund Wilson and the Kingdom of Heaven," Show, 1962 (Box 6)
    - "The Gloom of Philip Roth," Show, 1962 (Box 6)
    - "An Imaginary Dialogue with Theodore C. Sorensen," Show, 1962 (Box 6)
    - "In Defense of a Maltreated Best Seller," Show, 1962, and collected in Doings and Undoings, 1964 as "In Defense of James Baldwin” (Box 6)
    - "Masses, Classes and Social Criticism," Show, 1962 (Box 6)
    - "Byron's Princess of Parallelograms," Show, 1962 (Box 6)
    - "The '30s and Us," Show, 1962 (Box 6)
    - "Camus in His Twenties," Show, 1963 (Box 6)
    - "Hannah Arendt: Eichman in Jerusalem," Commentary, 1963 (Box 6)
    - "The Adventures of Saul Bellow," in Doings and Undoings, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "Consciousness and Poverty," Show, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "Love and Revolution," Book Week, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "The Face of Five Decades," New York Review of Books, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "The Melting Pot Blues," review of Shadow and Act, Book Week, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "Prurience Subverted, or the Redemption of Candy," Show, 1964 (Box 6)
    - "Purifying the West," Show, 1964 (Box 7)
    - "Putting the Cold War in Its Place," Show, 1964 (Box 7)
    - "Bringing the News," Book Week, 1965 (Box 7)
    - "In Defense of Editing," Harpers, 1965 (Box 7)
    - "Moynihan and What He Means," The New York Herald Tribune, 1965 (Box 7)
    - "Herman Kahn and the Unthinkable," Show, 1966 (Box 7)
    - "The United States, Its Problems, Impact and Image in the World," Seminar proceedings, 1969 (Box 7)
    - "Certain Anxiety," 1971 (Box 7)
    - "Does Literature Have a Future," Dialogue, 1974 (Box 7)
    - "Special Edition," 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - "Haig, and Reagan's Mandate," New York Times, 1980 (Box 7)
    - "The New Nationalism and the 1980 Elections," Public Opinion, 1980 (Box 7)
    - "AWACS," Washington Post, 1981 (Box 7)
    - "The New American Majority," 1981, published in various magazines including Commentary (Box 8)
    - "The Future Danger," Commentary, 1981, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Kissinger Reconsidered," Commentary 1981 (Box 9)
    - "New Defenders of Capitalism," Harvard Business Review, 1981 (Box 9)
    - "Tocqueville 1981," for Bayerischer Rundfunk, 1981 (Box 9)
    - "Why Reagan and Koch Are the Most Popular Politicians in America," New York, 1981 (Box 9)
    - "Camus and His Critics," New Criterion, 1982 (Box 9)
    - "F. R. Leavis: A Reevaluation," New Criterion, 1982 (Box 10)
    - "J'Accuse," Commentary, 1982, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - "The Massacre: Who Was Responsible," The Washington Post, 1982 (Box 10)
    - The Neo-Conservative Anguish over Reagan's Foreign Policy," New York Times Magazine," 1982, (1 folder) (Box 10, Box 11)
    - "A New Isolationism," published in Commentaire under title "Lettreaux Europeans, un Nouvel Isolationism American?" 1982 (Box 11)
    - "Our Aims and Israel's, "New York Times, 1982 (Box 11)
    - "Vietnam: Lessons of Defeat," New York Times, 1982 (Box 11)
    - "America Today," undated (Box 11)
    - C. P. Snow, undated and untitled (Box 11)
    - "The Cold War and the Future of the West," questionnaire from Partisan Review, undated (Box 11)
    - "D. H. Lawrence: The Novel Conversion," undated (Box 11)
    - "The Dream of Failure and the Dream of Success," undated (Box 11)
    - "Henry James's Jewish Heirs," undated (Box 11)
    - "In Defense of Pornography," undated (Box 11)
    - J. D. Salinger, undated and untitled, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - "James Jones," undated (Box 12)
    - "The Jew in American Society," undated (Box 12)
    - Lionel Trilling/Partisan Review, undated and untitled (Box 12)
    - "Love and Revolution," undated (Box 12)
    - "Lyndon B. Johnson," undated (Box 12)
    - "The Present and the Future Danger," undated (Box 12)
    - "The Rockwell Photograph," undated (Box 12)
    - "Strangers and Brothers," undated (Box 12)
    - "Young Generation," undated (Box 12)
    - "Why I Can't Get through the Charterhouse of Parma," undated (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous writings, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Published copies of articles by Podhoretz, 1959-1981, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Notes and sketches for essays (Box 13)
  - Books (Box 13)
    - Doings and Undoings, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Typescript (working title "A Reviewer's Decade"), (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous material related to publisher (Box 14)
      - Book reviews and articles, Feb. 1964-July 1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Making It, 1967 (Box 14)
      - Draft, typescript, (3 folders) (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous pages of transcript, typescript (Box 15)
      - Correspondence, Feb. 1967-July 1969 (Box 15)
    - Unpublished and uncompleted early draft of a book on the 1960s and 1970s, (5 folders) (Box 15)
    - "The Blacks," 1970s, related to book on the 1960s (Box 15)
    - "A Traitor to My Class," 1970s (early working title for Breaking Ranks) (Box 16)
    - Breaking Ranks, 1979 (Box 16)
      - False starts, typescript, (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - First draft, typescript, (4 folders) (Box 16)
      - Photocopies, (7 folders) (Box 17)
      - Photocopies, discarded pages (Box 18)
        - Third draft, typescript, superseded (Box 18)
          - Copy 1, (4 folders) (Box 18)
          - Copy 4, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 18, Box 19)
      - Final draft, typescript (Box 19)
        - Copy 1, (2 folders) (Box 19, Box 20)
        - Copy 2, (4 folders) (Box 20, Box 21)
        - Copyedited version (Box 21)
      - Page proofs, (1 folder); (7 folders); (2 folders) (Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24)
      - Uncorrected proof, Oct. 1979 (Box 24)
      - Excerpts (Box 24)
      - Miscellany relating to publication (Box 24)
      - Correspondence, June 1979-Dec. 1982, undated (Box 24)
      - Reviews (Box 24)
        - United States, Sept. 1979-Sept. 1980, undated (Box 24)
        - Foreign, Feb.-June 1980, undated (Box 24)
    - The Present Danger, 1980 (Box 25)
      - First draft, typescript (Box 25)
        - Copy I (Box 25)
        - Corrected by Podhoretz (Box 25)
        - Copyedited version, copy I (Box 25)
        - Copy 2 (Box 25)
      - Epilogue, miscellaneous pages and notes (Box 25)
      - Uncorrected proofs, July 1980 (Box 25)
      - Publisher's correspondence and miscellany related to U.S. edition (Box 25)
      - Miscellany related to foreign editions, (3 folders) (Box 25)
      - Correspondence, Mar. 1980-May 1981, undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
      - Book reviews and articles, Mar. 1980-May 1981, undated (Box 26)
      - Research materials, (3 folders); (1 folders) (Box 26, Box 27)
    - Why We Were in Vietnam, 1982 (Box 27)
      - Early unfinished draft, typescript (Box 27)
      - First draft, typescript, (2 folders) (Box 27)
      - Third draft, typescript, (2 folders) (Box 27)
      - Fourth draft, typescript, (3 folders) (Box 28)
      - Original copyedited manuscript, Typescript, (2 folders) (Box 28)
      - Galleys, (1 folder) (Box 28, Box 29)
      - Why We Were in Vietnam, 1982 (Box 29)
      - Page proofs for footnotes (Box 29)
      - Correspondence with and miscellany from publisher, (5 folders) (Box 29)
      - Correspondence, Aug. 1981-Dec. 1982 (Box 29)
      - Book reviews and articles (Box 29)
        - Jan.-May 1982, undated, (1 folder) (Box 29)
        - June 1982-Jan. 1983, (1 folder) (Box 30)
      - Research material, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 30, Box 31)
- Miscellany, 1958-1982 (Box 31-32)
  Newspaper clippings, printed material, and miscellaneous personal papers.
  Newspaper clippings and printed material are interfiled in chronological order. Duplicates are filed at the end of this section. Other Miscellany is filed at the end of the series.
  - Newspaper clippings and magazine articles concerning Podhoretz (Box 31)
    - 1958-1982, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Undated (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and articles, 1961-1982, undated, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous reprints (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous papers, mostly personal (Box 32)
- Addition, circa 1953-1986 (Box 33-43)
  - Speeches and Writings File, 1953-1986 (Box 33-40)
    Correspondence, notes, memoranda, typewritten drafts with handwritten annotations, galleys and page proofs of writings.
    Organized into writings, reviews, and speeches. Writings and reviews are arranged alphabetically; the speeches are arranged chronologically.
    - Speeches and Writings File, 1953-1986, undated (Box 33)
      - Writings (Box 33)
        - "American Liberalism," American Spectator, 1985 (Box 33)
        - "Appeasement by Any Other Name," Commentary, 1983, (3 folders) (Box 33)
        - "Arms Control," New York Times, 1985 (Box 33)
        - The Bloody Crossroads, 1986, (1 folder); (5 folders) (Box 33, Box 34)
        - "The Dialectic of Blame," Encounter, 1985 (Box 34)
        - "The Future of America," Partisan Review, 1984 (Box 34)
        - The God That Failed (Foreword) 1983 (Box 35)
        - "Henry Adams," New Criterion, 1983 (Box 35)
        - "If Orwell Were Alive Today," Harpers, 1983, (3 folders) (Box 35)
        - "Kundera," Commentary, 1984 (Box 36)
        - "Little Dorrit," New York Times, 1984 (Box 36)
        - "Military Intervention in South America?," New York Times, 1983 (Box 36)
        - "NATO and American Public Opinion," 1984 (Box 36)
        - "The Neo-Conservative Anguish over Reagan's Foreign Policy," New York Times, 1982 (Box 36)
        - "1984 Is Here: Where Is Big Brother?" Reader's Digest, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 36)
        - "A Plan for Spreading Misery, Not Wealth," New York Times, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 37)
        - "Proper Uses of Power," New York Times, 1983 (Box 37)
        - "Raymond Aron," 1985 (Box 37)
        - "Reagan, Man of Peace," New York Times, 1984 (Box 37)
        - "The Reagan Road to Detente," Foreign Affairs, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 37)
        - "Statue of Liberty: Lost Love," New York Magazine, 1986 (Box 38)
        - "The Terrible Question of Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn," Commentary, 1985, (2 folders) (Box 38)
        - Why We Were in Vietnam (paperback edition) 1982, (2 folders) (Box 38)
        - "Wisdom-What It Is... ," Bottom Line Personal, 1986 (Box 39)
        - Miscellany of writings, notes and drafts, circa 1953-1983 (Box 39)
        - Reviews (Box 39)
          - Caveat by Alexander M. Haig, Commentary, 1984 (Box 39)
          - Mayor by Edward Koch, Commentary, 1984 (Box 39)
          - Overdrive by William Buckley, Commentary, 1983 (Box 39)
          - Vietnam: A Television History, " by Stanley Karnow, 1983, (2 folders) (Box 39)
      - Speeches, 1983-1986, (7 folders) (Box 40)
  - Miscellany, circa 1975-1986 (Box 41-43)
    Diary, notebooks, general correspondence, interviews and statements, subject files and printed matter.
    Arranged alphabetically by type of material and usually chronologically therein.
    - Biographical material, circa 1975-1986, (2 folders) (Box 41)
    - Diary and notebooks, undated, (3 vols.) (Box 41)
    - General correspondence, 1977-1985, (2 folders) (Box 41)
    - Interviews and statements, 1978-1986, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 41, Box 42)
    - Printed matter, newspaper clippings, (1 folder) (Box 42, Box 43)
    - Subject file (Box 43)
      - Anti-nuclear policy, 1983 (Box 43)
      - Foreign policy, 1983-1985 (Box 43)